Guide to the National Maritime Union and Seafarers International Union Reference Files WAG.267
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Maritime Union and Seafarers International Union Reference Files
1878-1981, 2007-ongoing
1937-1969
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Seafarers International Union of North America
WAG.267
4.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
2 websites in 2 archived websites.
In monitoring their chief rival, the National Maritime Union (NMU), the Seafarers International Union (SIU) collected newspaper clippings on the NMU, as well as material written by and about its president, Joseph Curran. Material on the Waterfront Commission of New York Harbor (WCNYH), established in 1953 to investigate, deter, and remedy criminal activity and oversee fair hiring practice in New York Harbor, was also included. These reference files contain photocopies of clippings from the NMU Pilot, a quarterly publication, and from national papers such as the New York Times, San Francisco Call Bulletin, and New York World Telegram, many of them following Curran's career and documenting charges of fraud and racketeering on the New York City waterfront. The collection also includes files on the SIU, containing clippings and other historical material on the union and its presidents, Paul Hall and Frank Drozak.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Seafarers International Union, 1982. The accession number associated with this gift is 1982.006.
http://www.seafarers.org/ was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Archive. In 2015, this website was migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In 2019, http://seafarerslog.org/ was added to the web archive. The accession number associated with this website is 2020.010.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Historical Research Department of the Seafarers International Union (SIU) kept extensive files on Joseph Curran, president of the NMU from 1937 until his death in 1981. "Big Joe" Curran, then an inactive member of the conservative International Seaman's Union, founded the Seaman's Defense Committee during a wildcat strike in 1936 on the Panama Pacific Line's S.S. California. The Committee was renamed the National Maritime Union in 1937, and Curran became its first president. He served as a vice-president of the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) and ran for Congress on the American Labor Party ticket in 1940. After the second World War Curran took a major role in ridding the NMU of Communist-influenced officials and vigorously used the collective bargaining process to advance his union's agenda. In addition to national press coverage of the NMU, the SIU kept clippings of Curran's quarterly column in the NMU Pilot.
In addition to the NMU and Curran material, the SIU collected historical information, publications and clippings relating to its own activities and its president from 1957, Paul Hall. Hall, a staunch anti-Communist, defended his union against racketeers in the 1940s and 1950s and the encroachment of Jimmy Hoffa and the Teamsters in the 1960s. He was instrumental in the passing of the Energy Transportation Security Act of 1977. Also included are records of Hall's successor, Frank Drozak, SIU president from 1980 until his death in 1988.
Scope and Content Note
The Seafarers International Union of North America (SIU) reference files on the National Maritime Union (NMU) consist almost entirely of newspaper clippings from the NMU Pilot, a quarterly publication, and from national papers such as the New York Times, Boston Globe, and San Francisco Call Bulletin -- many of them following Joseph Curran's career and documenting charges of fraud and racketeering on the New York City waterfront. Of particular interest are the files of Curran's column in the NMU Pilot between 1937 and 1969. The Curran columns are organized by date, but subject headings (provided by the SIU staff) are included at the top of each photocopy. Also of note are folders containing background information on the SIU and its leadership, the SIU pamphlet, "How to get a Job on an Unorganized Ship" and a photocopy of "Seafarers Organizers Handbook" (SIU). Clippings from 1956 and 1963 document the work of the Waterfront Commission of New York Harbor (WCNYH).
The collection also contains the archived website for the Seafarers International Union, dating from 2007.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic.
Organized into 2 series:
I, Clippings, 1878-1981
II, Archived Websites, 2007-ongoing
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The following collections contain materials related to the National Maritime Union and Seafarers International Union Reference Files:
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Moving Images Collection (FILMS 001)
John Gladstone Papers (WAG 146)
International Longshoremen's Association: Reference Files of the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (WAG 055)
Marine Workers Historical Collection (TAM 125)
Marine Workers Oral History Collection (OH 030)
Clarence Reed Papers (WAG 015)
Randall B. (Pete) Smith: Maritime Radicalism Collection (TAM 203)
Henry Spira: National Maritime Union Rank and File Collection (TAM 418).
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Merchant mariners |x Labor unions |z United States.; Handbooks.; New York (N.Y.).; Biographies.; Clippings (information artifacts); Web sites.; Curran, Joseph Edwin, 1906-1981; Drozak, Frank; Seafarers International Union of North America; Waterfront Commission of New York Harbor; Hall, Paul; National Maritime Union of America; Seafarers International Union of North America
- Series I: Clippings
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot (I), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot (II), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1961-1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Curran, Joseph: Clippings (national newspapers), 1934-1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Curran, Joseph: Journal of Commerce Obituary and Biographical Information, Aug 1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hall, Paul: Clippings, 1946-1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Hall, Paul: Paul Hall – Pictorial Scrapbook Index (photocopy), 1885-1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Labor History (scholarly articles), 1908-1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Liberty Log: Newsletter of Liberty Ship Preservation, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1943, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings from the NMU Pilot, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1923, 1934-1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1939 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1941 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers) (I), 1946 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers) (II), 1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers) (I), 1948 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers) (II), 1948 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers) (III), 1948 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1949 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1952 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1960 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1961 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers), 1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers) (I), 1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - National Maritime Union: Clippings (national newspapers) (II), 1963 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - National Maritime Union: History (notes), 1934-1937 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Oil Preference Cargo Import Bill: Clippings, 1959, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Seafarers International Union: Clippings, 1930-1939 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Seafarers International Union: Clippings, 1940-1949 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Seafarers International Union: Clippings, 1950-1959 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Seafarers International Union: Clippings, 1960-1969 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Seafarers International Union: Clippings, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Seafarers International Union: Clippings, 1980-1989 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Seafarers International Union: Clippings (The Morning Call, San Francisco), 1878, 1886-1889 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Seafarers International Union: General, 1893-1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Seafarers International Union: Freightship Agreement, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Seafarers International Union of North America: Historical Information and Clippings (Frank Drozak and Paul Hall), 1957-1980, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Seafarers International Union: How to Get a Job on an Unorganized Ship, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Seafarers International Union: Research Resources in Maritime Labor History, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Seafarers International Union: Seafarers Organizers Handbook, 1940-1949 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Vocational Training: Clippings, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - War Bonus Strike: Clippings, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Waterfront Commission of New York Harbor: Clippings, 1956, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series II: Archived Websites, September 2007-ongoing; 2 websites in 2 archived websites.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
  Accruals
  New site crawls are accrued semiannually.
  Appraisal
  Crawl was limited to domains and subdomains of seafarers.org, seafarerslog.org, and in order to remain within the collection scope and data constraints. accounts.google.com was blocked to remain within scope and data constraints.
  Scope and Contents
  The Seafarers International Union (SIU), Atlantic, Gulf, Lakes and Inland Waters District/NMU, AFL-CIO, represents unlicensed United States merchant mariners sailing aboard U.S.-flag vessels in the deep sea, Great Lakes and inland trades. The union also represents licensed U.S. mariners in the Great Lakes and inland sectors. The website for SIU contains news from the union, labor and maritime news, training programs, courses, meeting listings, and issues of their newsletter, the Seafarer's Log. The series also contains the digital archive of the Seafarers International Union (SIU) which provides online access to back issues of the SIU newsletter (also titled 'Seafarers' Log') photographed from microfilm copies going back to 1939, as well as the Herb Brand Historic Files, which consist of photograph collections documenting the 1946 General Maritime Strike and the 1948 United Financial Employees Wall Street Strike. Archival objects in the SIU digital archive are viewable as PDF documents with descriptive metadata and social bookmarking. The collections can be browsed by collection and series or using an advanced search function.